<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacob and Esau. Election. Reprobation Opened and discussed by way of sermon at Pauls Crosse, March 4. 1622. By Humphry Sydenham Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101842</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837645</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1396:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacob and Esau. Election. Reprobation Opened and discussed by way of sermon at Pauls Crosse, March 4. 1622. By Humphry Sydenham Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Eliot's Court Press] for Iohn Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part of his "Five sermons, upon severall occasions", STC 23563.</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1982:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IACOB and ESAV: <hi>Election. Reprobation.</hi> OPENED AND DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVSSED BY WAY OF SERMON AT <hi>PAVLS</hi> CROSSE, <hi>March</hi> 4. 1622.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Humphry Sydenham</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> of <hi>Arts,</hi> and Fellow of WADHAM <hi>Colledge</hi> in OXFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. lib. 7. de Trinitate.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Qui videt haec, vel ex parte, vel per ſpeculum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nigmate, gaudeat cognoſcens Deum, &amp; gratias agat, qui verò non, tendat per pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem fidei ad videndum, &amp; non per cacitatem ad calumnian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for IOHN PARKER. 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1982:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1982:2"/>
            <head>TO MY MOST HONOVR'D FRIEND <hi>William Brouncker</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, This.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here I owe a iuſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and would pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it, I leſſe feare the cenſure of vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than of vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; you know the age is both tart, and nimble, in her Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe on thoſe which would be <hi>Men in Print;</hi> I haue found it; yet will rather hazard the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a weake man, than an vngrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> Howeuer, I deſire not ſo much to expoſe my <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1982:3"/>to the world, as my <hi>loyaltie,</hi> that others might take notice how much you haue beene mine in your cheriſhing of <hi>thoſe,</hi> and how I am euer yours in my expreſsions of <hi>this.</hi> He that doth but <hi>tacitely</hi> acknowledge the bounties of a <hi>noble</hi> friend, in a manner buries them, when he that proclaimes them, hath in a part requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; he hath repayed his honour, and therefore him, and ſo hath ſatisfied, though not reſtored. If this publike thankfulneſſe of mine, for thoſe daily fauours, ſhall meet with ſo mercifull an interpretation of yours, I eſteeme not any rigid one of the times; I cannot gloze with them, nor you, yet ſhall endeuour to be reputed one of thoſe who vnfeinedly honours you, and will doe, whilſt I weare the name, and title of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your euer friend, and ſeruant HVM: SYDENHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1982:3"/>
            <head>IACOB <hi>and</hi> ESAV.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 9.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He will haue mercy on whom he will haue mercy; and whom he will, he hardeneth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text holds ſome Analogie with the Times we liue in, fraught with no leſſe ſubtilty, than danger; and as an vndiſcreeter prouidence is ſoone oreſhot in thoſe, ſo in this too. We are not here then to cheat our Auditory with a thin diſcourſe; Myſterie is our Theame and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, the very Battlement and Pinacle of Diuinity, which he that too boldly climbes, falls headlong into errour. A taske, though perchance diſproportionable to youthfull vndertakings, and may from ſuch challenge the cenſure of a vaine-glorious enterpriſe: yet giue me leaue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, though not ſatisfaction, anſwer. In ſacred Riddles what wee cannot reſolue, giue vs leaue to contemplate; and what not comprehend, admire: where our pencill failes vs to limme in ſo curious a Portraiture, weele play <hi>Timanthes,</hi> and ſhadow with a vaile; and when our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is once <hi>non-pluſt,</hi> we are huſht in a contented wonder,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1982:4"/>Where we may behold the Almighty (in a full ſhower) powring downe his bleſſings vpon ſome, ſcarce deawing or ſprinkling them on others; ſoftning this Wax, and hardening that Clay, with one and the ſelfe ſame ſunne, (his will) and yet that will not clouded with iniuſtice. Here is that will not onely ſtagger, but entrance a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall apprehenſion; Not a circumſtance which is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually loaded with doubt and amazement, and whoſe diſcuſſing will no leſſe inuite than command attention. That which in common paſſages of Diuinity doth but tranſport our thought, in thoſe more myſticall will cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuate: Euery word is knotty, and full of brambles, and requires the hand of an exact induſtry.</p>
            <p>It behoues vs then to be wary of our choice, how ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we traffique here with corrupt antiquity (where but to taſte were to ſurfeit) or with that moderne Nauie of Expoſitors, where mixture of opinion will rather cloy than feed, and confound than informe our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. I deſire not to paraphraſe on a reuerend errour, nor to chaſtiſe there where I beg information. I ſhall onely requeſt gray haires thus farre to diſpence with me, that where their Candle burnes dimly and uncertainly, I may borrow light of a more glorious flame. Not then to beguile time and ſo noble an attention with quaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preamble, or diuiſion; The parts here are, as the perſons, and their condition, Two, <hi>Mercy</hi> for whom he will, and they are Sheepe; <hi>Hardening</hi> for whom he will, and theſe are Goats. Let vs firſt put them on the right hand, and we ſhall finde a <hi>Venite Benedicti, Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> here is mercy for you; After, theſe on the left hand, and we ſhall meet with an <hi>Itemaledicti, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> curſed,</hi> here is hardening for you: Both which, when wee haue in a carefull ſeparation orderly diſtinguiſhed, we ſhall make here the will of the Almighty as free from iniuſtice, as there his cenſure, <hi>He will haue mercy on whom he will, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1982:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PART. I.</hi> He will.</head>
               <p>THat the will of God is the principall efficient cauſe of all thoſe workes which he doth externally from himſelfe, ſo that there is no ſuperiour or precedent cauſe mouing and impelling it, ſhines to vs no leſſe from the eternity of his will, than the omnipotency; for with that double attribute <hi>Auguſtin</hi> doth inueſt it in his 2. booke <hi>contra Manichaeos, cap.</hi> 2. And ſeeing there is nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his will, as being eternall; nothing greater, as being omnipotent; we inferre with that learned Father, that <hi>Neque extra, vel vltra illam cauſa inquirenda;</hi> There is no cauſe either without, or beyond it, that being the ſource and fountaine of all cauſes, as by a more particular ſuruey of Gods workes we ſhall diſcuſſe hereafter. For il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration. In his eternall decree, why are ſome marked out as inheritours of his Sion? others againe expulſed, and baniſhed thoſe bleſſed Territories? they as veſſels of mercy, for the manifeſtation of his goodneſſe; theſe of furie, for the promulgation of his iuſtice? Doubtleſſe the wil, &amp; the <hi>bene-placitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> of the Almighty as the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; immediate cauſe, whereof if there be any more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, they haue all alliance and dependancy on it, <hi>Tanquam à principali intentione primi agentis.</hi> Like inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Orbes which haue their influence &amp; motion from a higher mouer. I need not trauaile far either for proofe or inſtance; our Chapter is bountifull in both. What was the cauſe that God did chuſe <hi>Iacob</hi> and reiect <hi>Eſau?</hi> The mediate and ſecondary cauſe, was, becauſe he loued <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and not <hi>Eſau.</hi> But why is his loue incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as it ſeemes, in a partiall reſeruation, peculiar to that more than this? I know not a more plauſible and higher motiue than his will. <hi>Inſiſtendum ergò in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culas,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1982:5"/>cuius vult, &amp; quem vult.</hi> Our enquiry here muſt be cautelous, and ſlow of foot, leſt wee run violently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to errour. Here is a <hi>cuius vult</hi> onely for him that hee hath mercy on, and but a <hi>quem vult</hi> for him he hardens; <hi>vltra quas procedere non l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cèt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caluin.</hi> Here is the vtmoſt Verge &amp; Pillar where reaſon durſt to coaſt; what is beyond is either vnknowne, or dangerous; how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſome vain-glorious braines (ambitious of myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and abſtruſer knowledge) haue inſcribed here their <hi>Multa pertranſiéunt, &amp; augibitur ſcientia.</hi> But in ſo ſtickle &amp; dangerous a torte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, how are they o'rewhelmed at laſt? and whilſt they ſo ventrouſly climbe this ſteeper turrer, throwned deſperately into hereſie? For mine owne part, I haue euer thought curioſity in diuine affaires but a quaint diſtraction, rather applauding an humble (yet faithful) ignorance, than a proud and temerarious know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And had ſome of the Fathers beene ſhot-free of this curious inſolence, they needed not haue retreated from former Tenents, &amp; ſo much in deared poſterity, no leſſe in the reuiew than retractation of laborious errors: Amongſt whom <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> (though ſince entituled <hi>Malleus Haereticorum</hi>) ſhared not a little in the 83. of his Queſtions, and 68. Where expounding our place of the Apoſtle, would thus vindicate the Almighty from iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; that God foreſaw that in ſome, <hi>Quo digni ſunt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatione;</hi> that in others, <hi>Quo digni ſunt obtuſione;</hi> ſo making God, will to depend on a foreſeene merit. A poſition that doth not onely repugne the diſcipline of holy ſtorie, but thwarts the maine tide &amp; current of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox antiquity, as in a fuller diſcourſe we ſhall diſplay anon: and therefore in his 7. Booke <hi>de Praedeſtinatione Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cap.</hi> 4. he doth chaſtiſe his former tenents with 2 <hi>Deus non elegit opera, ſed ſidem in praeſcientiâ;</hi> That God did not elect <hi>lacob</hi> for foreſeene workes, but faith. But becauſe in ſaith there is as well a merit, as in workes, he once more rectifies his opinion in the firſt of his Retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1982:5"/>and 23, where he doth peach his ſometimes ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and ingeniouſly declares himſelfe, that — <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum diligentius quaeſiuit, nec inuenit myſteria,</hi> he had not yet throughly ſifted that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. That there was a <hi>remnant according to the election of grace,</hi> which, if it did flow from a foreſeene merit, was rather reſtored than giuen, and therefore (at laſt) he informes his owne judgement, and his Readers thus; <hi>Datur qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fideli ſed data eſt etiam prius ut eſſet fidelis;</hi> Grace is given to the faithfull, but it is firſt given that he ſhould be faithfull. Hence <hi>Lumbard</hi> in his 1 booke, 41 diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pathetically, <hi>Elegit quos voluit Deus gratuitâ miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ, non quia fideles futuri erant, ſed ut eſſent, nec quià crediderant, ſed ut fierent credentes.</hi> God out of the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of his will, and bounty of his goodneſſe, hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen whom he pleaſed, not becauſe they were faithfull, but becauſe they ſhould be, and not of themſelues beleeuing, but made ſo. And therefore, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſim ſidelis,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.25. beares a remarkable emphaſis. <hi>I haue obtained mercie that I might be faithfull,</hi> not that I was. Here the Pelagian ſtartles, &amp; lately backt with a troope of Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, takes head againſt this truth, fancying and dreaming of certain cauſes without God, which are not ſubſiſting in God himſelfe, but externally mouing the will of God to diſpoſe and determine of ſeuerall euents, laying this as an unſhaken principle, <hi>Fidem eſſe conditionem in obiecto eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibili ante electionem;</hi> That faith and obedience (fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene of God in the Elect) was the neceſſary condition and cauſe of their election. I intend not here a pitcht field againſt the vpſtart Sectarie, for I ſhall meet him anon in a ſingle combat: my purpoſe now is to be but as a ſcour, or ſpie, which diſcouers the weakneſſe of his aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, not ſtands to encounter. And indeed both the time and place ſuggeſt me rather to reſolue, than debate; and convince, than diſpute an errour. That faith then, or any praeexiſting merit in the perſon to be elected; was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1982:6"/>the cauſe of his election, is neither warrantable by reaſon nor primitiue Authoritie. For God could not foreſee in the elect any faith at all, but that which in after times he was to crowne them with, and therefore not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as any precedent cauſe of election, but as the effect and fruit, and conſequent thereof.</p>
               <p>The primary and chiefe motive then is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. the good pleaſure of Gods will, which, prompted of it ſelfe, without any reference to praeexiſting faith, obedience, merit, as the qualities, cauſe, or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, hath powred grace on this man more than that; <hi>Non ſolum in Chriſto,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Synod. Dort.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed per Chriſtum.</hi> And therefore (as that late venerable Synode hath awarded it) <hi>Non ex illis conditionibus facta eſt, ſed ad illas;</hi> That election was not fram'd of theſe conditions, but to them, as to their effect and iſſue. And if we commerce a little with paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of holy ſtory, we ſhall find that our election points rather to the free will of God in his eternall councell, than to any goodneſſe in vs which God foreſaw: ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. where we read of the Gentiles, that many <hi>beleeued</hi> becauſe they were <hi>ordained</hi> to eternal life, and not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ordained</hi> becauſe they formerly <hi>beleeued.</hi> And if we will not ſuffer our minds to bee tranſported either with ſcruple or noueltie, the text is open, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>He hath choſen vs before the foundations of the world were laid, that we might be holy, not that we were.</hi> And in this very Chapter, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. The veſſels of mercy are firſt ſaid to be <hi>prepared</hi> to mercy, then <hi>cald:</hi> and therefore Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 86. Tract upon <hi>Iohn,</hi> out of a holy indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth check the inſolence of thoſe, <hi>Qui praeſcientiam Dei defendunt contra gratiam Dei;</hi> Which in matters of ſaluation, obſcure and extenuate the grace of God with the foreknowledge of God: for if God did therefore chuſe vs, becauſe he did know, and foreſee that wee would be good, he did not chuſe vs to make vs good, but wee rather choſe him, in purpoſing to be good,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1982:6"/>which if it did carry any ſhew either of probabilitie, or truth, we might queſtion our Apoſtle, who in his 8 here, and 29. no leſſe perſwades, than proues, that thoſe which God foreknew he did predeſtinate to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd</hi> to the image of his ſonne, and therefore God did not chuſe vs, becauſe before election there was a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie</hi> in vs, but becauſe from all eternitie he did elect vs, in time he made us <hi>conform'd</hi> to the image of his Sonne. Whereupon S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his fift booke, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iulianum.</hi> 3. <hi>chapt.</hi> thus, <hi>Nullum elegit dignum, ſea eligendo effecit dignum.</hi> God in the choiſe of his Elect, found none worthy, but in the chuſing made them worthy. Moreover, our election, which is of grace (as I yonder proued) could not ſtand if workes and merits went before it. <hi>Haec quippè non inuenit meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſed facit;</hi> Grace doth not find works in vs, but faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons them, according to that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>God hath from the beginning choſen you through ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirit, and not of works.</hi> Nay, ſome here ſo much aboliſh and wipe off all claime of merit, that they admit not Chriſt as the <hi>meritorious</hi> cauſe of our election. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſay they, the Scripture is thus farre our Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, That we are <hi>iuſtified</hi> by the blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Synod. Dort.</note> and <hi>reconciled</hi> to God by the death of his Sonne: but where are we informed that we are <hi>elected</hi> through his bloud, or <hi>praedeſtinated</hi> by his death? Indeed, in the 3 of <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. we finde a — <hi>ſic Dous dilexit,—God ſo loued the world that he gaue his Sonne.</hi> So that, not becauſe Chriſt died for vs, God loued, and choſe vs, but becauſe God loued and choſe us, therefore Chriſt died for vs. For ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>God ſetteth out his loue towards vs, that whilſt we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for vs.</hi> In matters therefore of election, we acknowledge not a cauſe more claſſicke than the <hi>Cuius vult</hi> here ſpecified, <hi>He will haue mercy on whom he will.</hi> Inſomuch that in the parable of the houſholder, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. I finde but a <hi>ſic volo,</hi> as a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1982:7"/>and iuſt cauſe of his deſignes. I will giue to this laſt as much as to thee; &amp; yet this Will ſo clothed with a diuine iuſtice, that God is not ſaid to will a thing to be done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is good, but rather to make it good, becauſe God would haue it to be done. For proofe whereof, a ſweet ſinger of our Iſrael inſtances in thoſe wonderfull paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of creation, where 'tis firſt ſaid that <hi>Deus cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uit,</hi> God created all things, and the <hi>Valdè bonum</hi> comes aloofe, he ſaw that they were all good, and the morall portends but this, That euery thing is therefore good, becauſe it was created, and nor therefore created becauſe it was good; which doth waſh, and purge the will of the Almighty from any ſtaine, or tincture of iniuſtice; for though that be the chiefe mover and director of all his proiects, as the prime and peremptory cauſe, doing this, becauſe hee will, yet we finde not onely <hi>ſanctitatem in operibus,</hi> but <hi>juſtitiam in vijs. The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes.</hi> Hereupon that great treaſurer of Learning and Religion, <hi>Zanchius</hi> in his 3 booke, <hi>de Natura Dei.</hi> and 4 <hi>chapter,</hi> diuides betweene the <hi>cauſe</hi> of Gods will, and the <hi>reaſon</hi> of his will: That though there be no ſuperiour cauſe of it, yet there is a iuſt reaſon, and a right end and purpoſe in it.<note place="margin">Morl. Clean. Lep.</note> Hence <hi>S. Ierome, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us nihil fecit quia vult, ſed quia eſt ratio ſic fieri;</hi> God doth nothing <hi>becauſe hee will,</hi> but becauſe there is a <hi>reaſon</hi> of ſo doing, in regard whereof it is not ſimply called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the will of God, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the good willof God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. So that in his ſacred reſolutions and deſignements, though we meet (ſometimes) with paſſages, wound vp in darkened terrour, the cauſe whereof wee may admire not ſcan; yet the drift and maine ends of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty haue been ſo backt with ſtrength of a iuſt reaſon, that we may rather magnifie his goodneſſe than tax his power; and applaud the calmneſſe of an indulgent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, than repine at the laſhes of an incenſed iuſtice. Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and goodneſſe are children of one burden, both
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1982:7"/>the lawfull iſſue of his will, which though foule mouthes of libertines haue ſtrangely baſtardized, making that the throne of tyranny, which is the rule of iuſtice, yet let them know that of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to his <hi>Sixtus; Iniuſtum eſſe non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, quod placuit Iuſto.</hi> To be God, and to be vniuſt, is to be God and not God. So faire a goodneſſe, was neuer capable of ſo foule a contradiction, and therefore (as the ſame father proſequutes) <hi>Iniquitatem damnare nouit, non facere:</hi> God knows how to iudge, not to commit a crime, and to diſpoſe, not mould it, and is often the father of the puniſhment, not the fact. Hence 'tis, that the dimneſſe of humane apprehenſion conceaues that (oftentimes) a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency in God, which is the monſter of our own frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; making God not onely to foreknow, but predeſtinate an euill, when the euill is both by growth, and concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ours, and if ought ſauour of goodneſſe in vs, Gods, not ours, yet ours too, as deriuatiue from God, who is no leſſe the Patron of all goodneſſe, than the Creatour, and 'tis as truly impoſſible for him to commit euill, as 'twas truly miraculous to make all that hee had made good. And therefore <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de Trinitate,</hi> makes it a <hi>Non poteſt fieri,</hi> a matter beyond the liſt and reach of poſſibilitie, that he ſhould be <hi>Artifex mali operis,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter &amp; enginer of a depraued act, who challengeth to himſelfe the title no leſſe of an vnblemiſhed Father, than of a Iudge. Our thoughts then ſhould not carry too loftie a ſaile, but take heed how they cut the narrow ſtraights, and paſſages of his will. A buſie prying into this Arke of ſecrets, as 'tis accompanied with a full blowne info<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſo with danger; Humilitie (here) is the firſt ſtaire to ſafetie; and a modeſt knowledge ſtands conſtantly wondering, whilſt the proud apprehenſion ſtaggers, and tumbles too. Here's a Sea vnnauigable, and a gulfe ſo ſcorning fathom, that our Apoſtle himſelfe was driuen to his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>O depth,</hi> and in a rapture, more of aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than contemplation, he ſtiles it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1982:8"/>
                  <hi>voluntatis ſuae myſterium,</hi> or (as <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates it,) <hi>Sacramentum,</hi> the Sacrament, and myſterie of his will, being ſo full of vnknowne turnings, and Meanders, that if a naked reaſon hold the clue, we are rather inuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, than guided in ſo ſtrange a Labyrinth.</p>
               <p>To enquire then the cauſe of Gods will, were an Act of <hi>Lunacie,</hi> not of <hi>Iudgement;</hi> for every efficient cauſe is greater than the effect, now there's nothing grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the will of God, and therefore no cauſe thereof. For if there were, there ſhould ſomething praeoccupate that will, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> to conceiue were ſinfull, to beleeue blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous. If any then (ſuggeſted by a vaine-glorious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie) ſhould aske why God did elect this man, and not that? we haue not onely to reſolue, but to foreſtall ſo bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an obiection: Becauſe he would. But why would God doe it? Here's a queſtion as guiltie of reproofe, as the author, who ſeekes a cauſe of that, beyond, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there is no cauſe found, where the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion wheeles, and reaſon runs giddy in a doubtfull gire: <hi>Compoſcat ſe ergo humana temeritas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; id quod non eſt non quaerat, ne id quod eſt non inueniat.</hi> Here a ſcrupulous and humane raſhneſſe ſhould be huſht, and not ſearch for that which is not, leſt it finde not that which is. For as the ſame Father, in his 105 <hi>Epiſt. Cur illum potiùs, quàm illum, liberet, aui non, ſcrutetur (qui poteſt) iudiciorum eius tam magnum profundum, ſed caueat praecipitium</hi>—. Let him hat can, deſcry the wonders of the Lord in this great deep, but let him take heed he ſinke not; and in his anſwer to the ſecond queſtion of <hi>Simplician: Quare huic ita, &amp; huic non ita, home tu quis es qui reſpondeas Deo? &amp; cur iſti ſic, illi aliter? Abſit vt dicamus Iudicium luti eſſe, ſed figuli.</hi> Why God doth to this man ſo, and to that not ſo, who dare expoſtulate? and why to this man, thus, to that, otherwiſe? farre be it, that we ſhould thinke it in the iudgement of the clay, but of the potter. Downe then with this aſpiring thought, this ambitious deſire of hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1982:8"/>knowledge, and make not curioſitie the picklocke of diuine ſecrets; know that ſuch myſteries are doubly bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp in the coffers of the Almighty, which thou maiſt ſtriue to violate, not open. And therefore if thou wilt needs treſpaſſe vpon deity, dig not in its boſome; a more humble aduenture ſutes better with the condition of a worme, ſcarce a man, or if ſo, expoſed to frailtie.</p>
               <p>'Tis a fit taske and imployment for mortalitie, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template Gods workes, not ſift his myſteries, and admite his goodneſſe, not blurre his iuſtice; And it hath beene euer the practice of primitiue diſcipline, rather to defend a diſparaged equitie, than to queſtion it, for ſo that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father (who euer mixt his learning with a deuout awe) in his 3 booke, <hi>cont. Iulianum,</hi> and 18 <hi>chapter, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt Deus, inſtus eſt Deus, poteſt aliquos ſine bonis meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis liberare, quia bonus eſt, non poteſt quemquam ſine malis damnare, quia iuſtus eſt.</hi> God is equally good and iuſt, he can ſaue ſome without reference to deſert, becauſe he is good, he cannot damne any man without a due deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, becauſe he is iuſt: Nay had God deliuered all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde into the iawes of deſtruction, we could not touch him with iniuſtice, but rather admire ſo darke and inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigable an equitie, which we may illuſtrate by worldly paſſages and humane contracts. If I were bankrupt of inſtance, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> could relieue me. A great man (ſaith he) lends two ſummes of money, to two ſeuerall men, who can tax him of obdurateneſſe, or iniuſtice, if at time of repayment he forgiue this man his debt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſatisfaction of that? for this liues not in the will and diſpoſall of the debtor, but of the creditor. So ſtands the caſe betweene frailty and omnipotencie. All men (which through <hi>Adam</hi> became tributaries to ſin and death) are one maſſe of corruption, ſubiect to the ſtroake of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine iuſtice, which, whether it be required or giuen, there is no iniquitie in God, but of whom required, and to whom giuen, 'tis in ſuch debtors inſolence to iudge,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1982:9"/>leſt God returne their ſaucineſſe with a —<hi>Non licet mihi quod volo facere?</hi> as the houſholder did the murmuring labourers in his vineyard. Is thine eie euill, becauſe I am good? And indeed I diſplay not a higher cauſe of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reprobation than diuine goodneſſe, which that learned Schoole-man, <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 23. <hi>art.</hi> 5. doth not onely illuſtrate but proue no leſſe by ſimilitude, than ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. For God (ſaith he) made all things for his goodneſſe ſake, that in things by him made, his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might appeare, but becauſe that goodneſſe is in it ſelfe, one, and ſimple: and things created cannot attaine to ſo diuine a perfection, it was neceſſary that that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhould be diuerſly repreſented in thoſe things, and hence 'tis that to the complement and full glory of the vniuerſe, there is in them a diuerſitie of degrees requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, of which ſome poſſeſſe a lower, and ſome a higher roome; and that ſuch a multiformitie may be preſerued in nature, God permits ſome euils to be done, leſt much good ſhould be anticipated: —<hi>Voluit itaque Deus in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, quantum ad aliquos, quos praesteſtinet, ſuam reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentare bonitatem, per modum miſericordiae, parcendo illis, quantum verò ad alios, quos reprobet, ſuam oſtendi bonita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem per modum iuſtioiae, puniendo eos.</hi> God in thoſe hee elects, would ſhew his goodneſſe by way of mercie in ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe, in others he reprobates, his goodneſſe too, by way of iuſtice in puniſhing them. And therefore our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here not onely magnifies the riches of his glory vpon veſſels of mercie, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. but his long parience too, to veſſels of wrath, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. So that in his houſe there are not onely thoſe of gold and ſiluer, but of wood and earth too, <hi>and ſome to honor, ſome to diſhonor,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. Of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if any mutinous or ſawcy ignorant deſires a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon beyond Gods will, I haue no anſwer but that of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> in his 22 Sermon, <hi>de verb Apoſt. Turatiocinare, ego mirer, in diſputa, ego credam: altitudinem video, ad profundum non peruenio;</hi> Diſpute and reaſon he that durſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1982:9"/>while my thought and beleefe ſtand at a bay, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; I ſee there is a height, but cannot reach it, and know this gulfe, not fathome it. For as in things naturall (it is <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſimilitude) when all the firſt matter is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, why one part of it ſhould be vnder the forme of fire, another vnder the forme of earth, there may be a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aſſigned, that there might be a diuerſity of <hi>ſpecies</hi> in things naturall: but why this part of matter ſhould be rather vnder the forme of fire, and that vnder the forme of earth, depends only on the ſimplicity of Gods will; &amp; as it hangs too on the wil of the Architect, that this ſtone ſhould be rather in this part of the wall, and that in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, although reaſon and art require that other ſtones ſhould be in one part of the Edifice, &amp; others in another. Neither is there for this iniquity in God, that he doth not proportion his gifts in a ſtrict equality, for it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reaſon and truth of iuſtice, if the effect of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination ſhould be of debt, and not of grace; for in thoſe thing which are of an vnreſtrained freedome, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man (out of the iuriſdiction of his owne will) may giue to whome he will, more or leſſe, without the leaſt diſparagement of iuſtice: And therefore to thoſe recoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling diſpoſitions w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> mutter at a free hounty, heaped on others without refere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to deſert, I wil vſurpe that of the Parable, <hi>Tolle quod tuum eſt, &amp; vade.</hi> And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding though the will of God be the independent prime cauſe of all things, ſo that beyond it there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, and without it there is no reaſon of Gods acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yet it is not the ſole and particular cauſe, for there are many ſecondary concurring with the firſt, by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, the will of God brings his intendments to an iſſue. As in matters of our ſaluation the will and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of man ſhakes hands with that of God, for though without him we finde a <hi>Nil poteſtis facere, Ioh.</hi> 15.52. Ye can doe nothing; yet aſſiſted by his will, and the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and effectuall operations of his grace, our will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operates
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1982:10"/>with Gods. Elſe how could <hi>Dauid</hi> pray to him to be his helper, vnleſſe he himſelfe did endeauour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? or how could God command vs to doe his will, except the will of man did worke in the performance of it?<note place="margin">Lum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> It is true (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) we finde a <hi>Deus operatur omnia in omnibus,</hi> but we no where finde a <hi>Deus credit omnia in omnibus. Noſtrum itaque eſt credere, &amp; velle, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius autem dare credentibus, &amp; volentibus facultatem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi:</hi> To will, and to beleeue is ours, but to giue the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of operation to them that will and bleeue, is Gods. <hi>I haue laboured more than they all, yet not I, but the grace of God with me,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. Why God therefore doth ſaue ſome men, there is more to be alleaged than this, God would haue them to be ſaued; for if this laurell doe beautifie our triumph we muſt encounter, hee that will haue this Crowne muſt tug for it, and this prize, muſt wreſtle, <hi>Qui creauit te ſine te, non ſaluat te ſine te.</hi> He that hath created thee without thy ſelfe, will not ſaue thee without thy ſelfe. And therefore thoſe whom God from all eternity hath deſtined to ſaluation, hee hath in a like priuiledge deſtined to the meanes: But why thoſe meanes, not communicable to all, many a buſie endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour hath ſtrugled for a reaſon, not compaſt it. Out of more than a double Iurie of Interpreters, which I haue (not with a little diſtraction) obſerued, wauing here in doubtfull opinion, <hi>Hugo de Sancto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictore</hi> giues thus his verdict. Gods grace is indifferently exhibited to all men, to the elect and reprobate, but all doe not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually lay hold on it. Some no leſſe neglect, than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe Gods grace, and when its comfortable beames ſhall ſhine vpon them, they ſhut their eies againſt it, and will not behold it, and God in iuſtice with-drawes his grace from theſe men, becauſe they with-draw themſelues from his grace. <hi>Eſt enim in gratiâ quemadmodum in ſolis radio</hi> (ſaith he) There is a proportion betwixt the raies of the Sunne, and the eie, and betwixt the ſoule of man, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1982:10"/>the grace of God. The eie is ordoined by nature to be the organ of the ſight, and yet the eie cannot ſee except the Sunne enlighten it; neither can the Sunne make any thing elſe ſee but the eie in man, for it may ſhine vpon our hand or foot, neuertheleſſe the hand or foot ſhall ſee nothing: ſo the ſoule hath a poſſibility to merit by her naturall abilities, but that poſſibility ſhall be vaine and fruitleſſe, vnleſſe it be quickned by the powerfull opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods grace, which grace, if it ſhall once actuate it, then the ſoule will be able to attaine to that double life of grace here, of glory hereafter. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde totum eſt ex gratiâ, ſic tamen vt non excludatur meritum.</hi> Whence he would haue all to hang on grace, yet ſo that wee exclude not merit. But this inference is many ſtories aboue my reach, and in the greenneſſe of my iudgement, there is little truth in the conſequence, and palpable contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the conſequent. For how can the merits of man challenge any thing, if all flow from the grace of God? Yes (ſaith <hi>Hugo</hi>) euen as a weake child which cannot yet goe alone, ſhould be led by the Nurſe, a man cannot ſay that the childe goeth of himſelfe, but by the aſſiſtance of the Nurſe; and yet the Nurſe could not make the childe goe, vnleſſe he were naturally inclinde to that motion: ſo the ſoule of man is ſaid to merit by the aid of grace, and by her owne naturall inbred ability, but all the glory of the merit muſt be aſcribed to God, becauſe the ſoule can doe nothing without the ſupport and grace of God. Whencel can gather no truth but this, that in <hi>ſolo homine ſit peten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia logica ad ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That a man only maybe ſaued without apparant contradiction; no vnreaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is capable of that euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe and beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall viſion; and the ſoule of a beaſt is no more able to ſee God, than a ſenceleſſe ſtocke to behold a viſible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. For man onely hath a paſſiue power to ſaluation, and man before his conuerſion hath a paſſiue power on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And therefore the ſimilies afore propoſed, if they be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1982:11"/>referred to the ſoule before the conuerſion, are falſe, and beare no proportion, for then the ſoule is ſtarke blinde, and dead in treſpaſſes, and cannot looke on the grace of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, or moue one iot in the courſe of Chriſtianity: But after the conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when God ſpeaks <hi>Ephata</hi> to the ſoule, be opened, when the vnderſtanding is illuminated, and ſcales of errour once drop from the eies, then it may hold ſome correſpondency with truth. As therefore in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our conuerſion, ſo of election too, all hangs on Grace, and this grace in a holy reſeruation limited to a narrow Tribe, for the <hi>cuius vult</hi> here inſinuates no more, and <hi>He will haue mercy on whom he will,</hi> ſounds in a direct aequiualence with this, <hi>He will haue mercy</hi> onely on ſome; of which ſome there is a definite and ſet num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, vncapable of augmentation, or diminution, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thoſe new ſprung Sectaries,<note place="margin">Arminians.</note> out of a turbulent braine and thirſt of cauillation, blaſpheme the eternity of Gods decree, making our election mutable, incompleat, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionate, ſubiect to change and reuocation, and what other ſtranger birth and prodigie of opinion, which <hi>I</hi> conceiue not without a holy impatience and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And whereas our Fathers of old haue maintained, euen to the ſword and fagot, the decree of election to be no leſſe eternall than irreuocable, theſe would faine lull our beleefe with innouation of vpſtart diſcipline, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering no leſſe the number than the condition of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect into the ſtate of reprobate, and of the reprobate into the elect. And (as the Deuill did to Chriſt) they vrge Text and reaſon for it. For God (ſay they) cannot giue grace to whom he doth giue grace, which if hee ſhould doe an elect may be damned; and hee can giue grace to him he doth not giue grace too, which if he doe, a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate may be ſaued, and ſo a reprobate may become an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and an elect a reprobate. Thus they ſhoot by an indirect aime, and ſaile by a wrong Compaſſe, for wee enquire not here of Gods power, but of his will, not what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1982:11"/>he can doe, but what he hath reſolued to doe. Againe, it ſeemes no conſequence, God can ſaue or damne a man, therefore this man can be ſaued or damned,<note place="margin">Huge de Saxcto Victore in cap. <hi>9.</hi> ad Rom.</note> 
                  <hi>Non enim poſſe Dei ſequitur poſſe noſtrum,</hi> Gods power ſtands not in relation to ours: as if God would otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme mankinde than by the death of his Sonne. (As there was another meanes poſſible (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>) but not more conuenient.) That therefore mankinde could o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be redeemed; and if God had this in his power, that it ſhould be therefore in mans too? Could not God (if he would) haue ſaued <hi>Iudas?</hi> doth it therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that <hi>Iudas</hi> could be ſaued? No, for though this be too ragged and ſtonie for a popular capacity to digge through; yet if wee looke backe a little into the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Gods decree, wee ſhall finde that which will no leſſe relieue our vnderſtanding, than remoue our ſcruple; where things from euerlaſting haue ſuch a doome, which is not malleable either by change or reuocation, <hi>For the Lord of hoſts hath determined, and who can diſanull it? and his hand is ſtretched out, and who can turne it away? Iſay</hi> 14.27. Seeing then that election is from eternity, and that not obnoxious to mutability or corruption, we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther curtaile the elect of their primatiue glory, nor of their number. Which though they be a little flocke, (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that herd and large droue of the damned) yet in thoſe ſacred volumes of Gods diuiner Oracles, we finde them numberleſſe. So <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Theſe things I beheld, and loe, a great multitude which none could number of all nations and kinreds, and people, and tongues, ſtood before the throne, and before the Lambe, cloathed with long white robes, and palmes in their hands.</hi> Whence thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for the Romiſh See, would hew out a way to vniuerſall grace; making our election <hi>generall, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde, indefinite,</hi> and would haue Chriſts death no leſſe <hi>meritorious,</hi> than <hi>propitiatory</hi> for the ſinnes of the whole world. A <hi>quaere</hi> long ſince on foot betweene <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1982:12"/>and <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and ſince in a fiery skirmiſh betweene the Calumiſt and the Lutheran, out of whoſe mud and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption there hath beene lately bred the Arminian, a Sect as poiſonous as ſubtill, and will no Ieſſe allure than betray a flexible and yeelding iudgement. For our own ſafety then, and the eaſier oppugning of ſo dangerous a ſuggeſtion, let vs examine a little of the extent &amp; bounds of this grace, which Diuines cut into theſe three ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, in <hi>Gratiam Praedeſtinationis, vocationis, &amp; iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationis. Gratia Praedeſtinationis,</hi> is that of eternity, the wombe and Nurſery of all graces, whereby God loued his elect, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Gratia vocationis,</hi> a ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace, by which God cals vs, and by calling preſcribes the meanes of our ſaluation. And this grace hath a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proſpect, Either to that which is externall, <hi>in libro Scripturae,</hi> or <hi>creaturae,</hi> where God did manifeſt himſelfe as well by what he had made, as by what he had written, or to that which is internall, of illumination, or renoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of that in the intellect only, which a reprobate may lay claime to, of this in the heart, which by a holy reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and incommunicableneſſe is peculiar to the elect, <hi>Gratia inſtificationis,</hi> which is not a grace inherent, but beſtowed, and ſtands as a direct. Antipode to humane merit. Yet not that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which the Schooles chriſten with a <hi>gratia gratis data,</hi> any gift which God out of his free bounty hath beſtowed vpon vs beyond our deſert, as Prudence, Temperance, and the like; for in theſe the heathen had their ſhare, whoſe ſingular endowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts haue made poſterity both an admirer, and a debter; but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Gratia gratum faciens,</hi> a gift perfect, and fanctified, which doth ſo qualifie the receiuer, that hee is not onely accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but glorious in the eyes of the beſtower, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Faith, Hope, &amp; the third ſiſter, Charity, which no leſſe recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile than iuſtifie vs before God.</p>
               <p>We conclude then, that the externall grace which the creature affordeth vs, is not limited to a priuate number,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1982:12"/>but to all; yet we denie the power and vertue of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it. We allow a ſufficiencie of redargution for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicting the heathen, who when they knew God, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him not as God, and therefore are both deſperate and inexcuſable. Moreover the grace which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture affor deth vs, as it is not vniuerſall, ſo not of abſolute ſufficiency for faluation, but onely in <hi>genere mediorum externorum,</hi> (as the Schooles ſpeake) becauſe it doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vs the meanes how we may be ſaued, but it doth not apply the meanes that we are ſaued. Againe, that grace of Illumination is more peculiarly confined, and if by the beames of that glorious Sunne which enlightneth euery man that comes into the world, we attaine to the knowledge of the Scripture, yet the bare knowledge doth not ſaue vs, but the application. But the grace of regeneration is not onely a ſufficient, but an effectuall grace, and as 'tis more powerfull, ſo 'tis more reſtrained; they onely partake of this bleſſednes, whom God hath no leſſe enlightned, than ſanctified, and pointed out, then ſealed, men inueſted in white robes of ſinceritie, whoſe delinquencies, though ſometimes of a deepe tincture, are now both diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed with, &amp; obliterated, not becauſe they were not ſinfull, but becauſe, not imputed: ſo inuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crous, and hidden are Gods eternall proiects, that in thoſe he relinquiſheth, or ſaues, his reaſon, is his will; yet that as farre diſcoaſted from tyranny, as iniuſtice. The <hi>Quare</hi> we may contemplate, not ſcan, leſt our miſpriſion grow equall with our wonder. And here in a double ambuſh dangerouſly lurke the Romaniſt and the Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, men equally ſwolne with rancor of malice, and po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition: and with no leſſe violence of reaſon, than impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, preſſe the vertue of Chriſts death for the whole world. Alas! we combat not of the price and worth of Chriſts death, but acknowledge That an able ranſome of a thouſand worlds; but the ground of our duell tends to this, whether Chriſt dying propoſed to himſelfe the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1982:13"/>ſaluation of the whole world. We diſtinguiſh then—<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chriſti, &amp; gratiam Chriſti.</hi> The merits of Chriſt and the gracious application of thoſe merits. His merits are able to allay the fury of his incenſed Father, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile vnto him the very reprobates: but the application of thoſe merits are reſtrained to the Elect, for they onely are capeable of ſo great a bleſſedneſſe. For proofe wherof we haue not only that venerable Bench and Councell of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Schoole-men, but alſo a higher court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to appeale vnto, the Regiſters and penmen of ſacred Chronicles, Euangeliſts, &amp; Apoſtles, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> punctually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate Chriſts death onely for his own, for his Church, for his Brethren, for thoſe whoſe head hee was, laying down his life for ſome, and ſhedding his blood for ſome, for his ſheepe, his little flock, his peculiar Prieſthood, his tabernacle, body, ſpouſe, his Canaan, Sion, Ieruſalem, his Ambaſſadors, Saints, Angels, in a word this <hi>Cuius vult,</hi> The Elect. I'le not beat your eares with a voluminous ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of text and Fathers, I'le draw only one ſhaft out of this holy quiuer, and direct it to the Roman aduerſary, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if he ſhall repell or put by, I'le proclaime hereafter a perpetuall truce. The maine and chiefe cauſe that impeld Chriſt to die, was his loue, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. But Chriſt loued not all, but his own <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. Therefore Chriſt died not for all, but for his owne. The Ieſuite here retraicts, and we haue none now left to encounter vs but the Arminian; who (like a cunning Fencer) hath many a quaint flouriſh, and with a falſe blow ſometimes ſtaggers, not wounds his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary. The part moſt in dangered, is the eie of our Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and iudgement which he thus dazzels with a ſubtile nicety. That Chriſt hath obtained reconciliation for all, for <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moulin</hi> in his Anatomy of Arminianiſme</note> but not as they were reprobates, but as they were ſinners; For God (ſaith he) did equally intend, and deſire the ſaluation of all, and the reaſon why they were not ſaued was their incredulitie, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying of this gracious reconciliation and attonement.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1982:13"/>Thus they would betray weakneſſe into the hands of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; and for a fairer gloſſe, and gilding of this their treachery, they diſtinguiſh —<hi>inter Impetrationem, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicationem;</hi> Pretending that Chriſt did impetrate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation for all, but the application of that leanes wholly to the elect. How crazy and ill tempered this poſition is, wee'le declare briefly. Firſt, wee deny that Chriſt by his death hath impetrated reconciliation for all, for <hi>Saul,</hi> or <hi>Iudas:</hi> Neither can our thought, much leſſe our beleefe giue way to ſo ſtrange a Paradox,<note place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> That remiſſion of ſinnes is obtained for thoſe whoſe ſinnes are not remitted, or that ſaluation was purchaſed for thoſe whom God from all eternity had decreed to condemne. Againe, we acknowledge Chriſts death ſufficient for all, all beleeuers, nay all, if they did beleeue. But that <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Iudas</hi> or the reſidue of that curſed Hierarchy ſhould reap the benefit of his Paſſion, we vtterly diſclaime as erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hereticall. For if Chriſt by his death hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled <hi>Iudas,</hi> how i'ſt that <hi>Iudas</hi> ſuffers for his ſinnes? for we cannot without impeachment both of his mercy, and iuſtice too, ſay that Chriſt ſuffered for <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſins, yet <hi>Iudas</hi> is damned for thoſe ſinnes; And ſince Chriſt as he is God, hath from euerlaſting deſtined <hi>Iudas</hi> to damnation, how i'ſt that the ſame Chriſt, as he is man, and mediator betweene God and man, ſhould reconcile <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> whom from eternity he had reprobated? Againe, if Chriſt hath obtained reconciliation for all men, then none ſhall be borne without the couenant of Chriſt, ſo that of the Apoſtle will be falſe: That, <hi>By nature we are all borne the children of wrath, Epheſ.</hi> 2. And can we true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſtiled the children of wrath, if reconciliation be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for all men without exception? And if all infants borne without the couenant are reconciled, <hi>Cur non cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti crudelitate in cunis iugulauimus?</hi> (ſaith the learned <hi>Moulin</hi>) why doe we not in a mercifull cruelty murther them in their cradles? for then their ſaluation were ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1982:14"/>but if they ſuruiue, they are nouriſhed in Paganiſme, infidelitie, which are the beaten roades and highwayes to deſtruction. And if we ſcan (ſaith he) the nicety of theſe words, the obtaining of reconciliation to be applied, and the application of reconciliation obtained, wee ſhall finde it a meere curioſitie to harrow and perples the braine, and torture the vnderſtanding, ſince Chriſt hath neuer obtained that which he hath not applied, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath he applied that which he hath not obtained. Yet theſe men either of a head-ſtrong opinion, or learned madneſſe, are ſo violent in the proſecution of their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, that no ſtrength of anſwer will ſatisfie their obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor modeſtie of language ſuppreſſe their clamour, but a foule mouthed <hi>Forſterus</hi> will bray out his witty ſpleene with an —<hi>Error, &amp; furor Zuinglianorum.</hi> His reaſons are as ſlender as they are many (the vertigoes and impoſtures of agiddie braine) fitter for ſilence, than rehearſall, and for ſcorne than conſutation. Wee apply then; Is grace vniuerſally bountifull, and mercy open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſted vnto all? What meane then thoſe Epithites of outcaſt, curſed, damned, and that triple inſcription of death, hell, and damnation? are they either of pollicie or truth? Are they things reall, or fancied onely to bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare and awe mortalitie? What would the Throne por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend? Iudge, aduerſarie, Sergeant, priſon, or thoſe horrid tones of worme, fire, brimſtone, howling, gnaſhing? Is the Scripture the Anuill of vntruth, or are theſe things no more than faigned and imaginary? What will thoſe flames of your threatned purgarory proue at laſt, but the Chimaera and coinage of a phantaſticke braine? And a 500 yeares indulgence, but the ſharke and legerdemaine or your Lord God the Pope? Either your opinion is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or your priſon, both which muſt fleet with your holy Fathers honour, if the armes of mercie be expanded to all. Againe, are the merits of Chriſt appliable to all? Sweare, whore, drinke, prophane, blaſpheme, and (if there
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1982:14"/>be in that Alcharon, and curſed rolle, a ſinne of a fairer growth) baffle the Almighty at his face. Thinkeſt thou that heauen was euer guiltie of ſuch treaſon againſt her Soueraigne? or that it will euer entertaine a gueſt ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the height of diſſoluteneſſe and debauſhment? No, thou muſt know that one day there will be a dread full ſummons, either at thoſe particular accounts, at the houre of Death, or at the generall audit of the laſt trumpe, when thou ſhalt meet with a new Acheldema and vale of Hinnom, places no leſſe of terror than of torment, the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery dungeon, and the burning Tophet, where the fury of the great Iudge realls in a floud of brimſtone, and his reuenge boiles in a firy torrent, limitleſſe, and vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. On the other ſide happily maiſt thou ſlumber, without howle; or skreeke of conſcience, thou wounded and deiected ſpirit; Thou whoſe glorious ornaments are but ſack cloth and aſhes, and thy choiſeſt fare but the bread of ſorrow and contrition. Know there is balme of Gilead for the broken-hearted ſinner, and oile of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for thoſe which mourne in Sion. Behold how thy Sauiour comes flying downe with the wings of his loue, and ſweepts away thy ſinnes that they ſhall neither tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally ſhame thee, nor eternally condemne thee: Who ſhall wipe off all teares from your eyes, and lodge you in the boſome of old <hi>Abraham,</hi> where there is bliſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable for euer. And thus I haue ſhewed you the happineſſe of ſheepe vnder the ſtate of mercie; Time bids me now to reflect on the miſery of Goats, as they are vnder the condition of hardening.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1982:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PART. II.</hi> He hardeneth.</head>
               <p>WHat? he that is rich in goodneſſe, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies aboue all his workes? he that mournes in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret for our offences, and vowes that he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, will he harden? How can this ſtand either with his promiſe, or mercy, or iuſtice? Gods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuealed proiects are full of wonder, which if our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion cannot diue to, our beliefes muſt ſound. <hi>Occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſſe poſſunt, iniuſta non poſſunt,</hi> fraught they may be with ſullen and darker riddles, neuer with iniuſtice. Let vs firſt then take a ſuruey of Mans heart, and ſee to what miſeries the hardneſſe of it hath expoſde our irregular predeceſſors, and after try whether we can make proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the mother of ſo deformed an iſſue. And here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while let vs obſerue S. <hi>Bernard</hi> tutoring his <hi>Eugenius, Cor durum,</hi> a heart, which the ſofter temper of Gods working ſpirit leaues to mollifie, and its owne corrupt affections begins once to mould. Like that of <hi>Naball,</hi> to be all ſtone, becomes at laſt ſo cauterized, <hi>Vt ſemetipſum non exhorreat quià nec ſentit,</hi> that it is ſo farre from ſtarting at its owne vglineſſe, that it is non-ſenſible of deformity. And hence <hi>Theodoret</hi> defines it to be <hi>pranam animi affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem,</hi> a corrupt and depraued affection of the minde, which if man once giue way to, hee is ſo ſcreen'd both from Gods mercy and truth; that though it be about him, and in the maſterdome and dominion of his beſt ſenſe, <hi>Non cernit tamen, nec intelligit,</hi> yet his eyes are as blinde intelligencers to belieue, as his vnderſtanding. And againſt ſuch that ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> breakes out into his paſſionate complaint, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquè quò filij hominum, vſquè quò?</hi> O ye ſonnes of men, how long will ye turne my honour into ſhame, how long? and that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomartyr
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1982:15"/>
                  <hi>Stephen,</hi> in his Oration to the refractary Iewes. <hi>Durâ ceruice,</hi> O ye ſtiffe-necked and vncircumcized of heart and eares, yee doe alwaies reſiſt the holy Ghoſt. And indeed ſuch hearts are but the Wardrobes and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequers of future miſchiefe, whoſe keyes are not in the cuſtodie of the Almighty, but thine owne boſome. For ſo that great Doctor of the Gentiles, <hi>Secundum impoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens cor tuum theſauriſas iram:</hi> According to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency of thine owne heart, <hi>thou treaſureſt vp wrath</hi> (to thy ſelfe) <hi>againſt the day of wrath.</hi> How then can that eye which ſhould be fixed either on the tenderneſſe or mercy of his Creator, glance ſo much on his iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as to make that the Midwife of ſo foule a progenie? Obduration was neuer the childe of goodneſſe, neither can a ſinne of ſo baſe a deſcent lay claime to omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. It ſtands not (I dare ſay) with Gods power, I am ſure, his will, to reconcile two enemies in ſuch an extre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mity of oppoſition. Doe ſweet water and puddle flow immediatly from one and the ſelfe-ſame ſpring? light and darkneſſe from the ſelfe-ſame Sunne? I know there is a ſtiffe-necked and bliud-fold Tribe, which God hath left, not made the ſtorie of his vengeance; whoſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are too dull and drouſie in his ſeruice. Men creſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen in deuotion, whoſe hearts are ſo dead in their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to him, that they ſeeme ſpiritleſſe, hauing all the powers &amp; faculties of their ſoule benummed, and their conſcience without pulſe or motion. And of theſe the Prophet, <hi>Incraſſatum eſt cor populi, Their heart is as fat as brawne.</hi> Theſe ſticke not to belch open defiance in the face of the Almighty, and with thoſe Miſcreants in <hi>Iob.</hi> are ready to expoſtulate with eternity. <hi>Quis eſt omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens vt ſeruiemus ei? Who is the Lord that we ſhould ſerue him?</hi> Such haue forehead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of braſſe, which no ſhame can bore through: and (as the Prophet ſpake of <hi>Iuda</hi>) <hi>a face of whoredome which refuſeth modeſty.</hi> But Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> in his 10. <hi>Homily</hi> vpon <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> hath proclaimed their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1982:16"/>doome. <hi>Frontem cordis in impudentiam aperit culpa fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens, vt quo crebrius committitur, eò minus de illa com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittentis animus verecundetur:</hi> Frequency of ſinning doth fleſh vs in immodeſty, aſſiduity, in impudence. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences that are cuſtomarie are not eaſie of dimiſſion, and if thou once entertaine them as thy followers, they will quickly intrude as thy companions. Sinnes that are ſed with delight, with vſe, are as dangerous as thoſe of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite: which oftentimes proue no leſſe inſeparable, than hereditary; to doe well is as impoſſible to theſe, as not to doe ill; So can aſſiduity make a ſinne both delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and naturall. <hi>Can the Aethiop change his skinne, and the Leopard his ſpots? then may yee alſo doe well which are accuſtomed to doe euill.</hi> That ſinne then is irrazable which is ſo ſteeled with cuſtome, and may vnder goe the cenſure of that ſometime Citie of God; <hi>Inſanabilis eſt dolor tuus:</hi> Thy ſinne is written with a pen of iron, and with a claw of a Diamond is engrauen on the table of thy heart. How then can wee without ſacriledge, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of diuine honour, make God the father of ſo foule and vnwaſhed a crime? Obduration is the iſſue of thine owne tranſgreſſion. <hi>Perditio tua ex te, ô Iſrael:</hi> If de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction dog thee, thanke thy corrupt affections, not blame thy maker, for he doth but leaue thee, and they harden. To lay then (with ſome depraued libertines) the weight and burden of our ſinnes on the ſhoulder of Predeſtination, and make that the wombe of thoſe ſoule enormities, may well paſſe for an infirmity, not for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and indeed thus to ſhuffle with diuine goodneſſe, is no leſſe fearefull, than blaſphemous. For, though God from eternity knew how to reward euery man, either by crown, or puniſhment—.<hi>Nemini tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut neceſſitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut voluntatem intulit delinquendi,</hi> yet he neuer enioyned any man either a neceſſity, or a will to ſinne. If any then fall off from goodneſſe, hee is hurried no leſſe with the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his owne perſwaſion, than concupiſcence; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1982:16"/>in thoſe deſperate affaires, Gods will is neither an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medler, hor compartner, <hi>Cuius ope ſcimus multos, ne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berentur, retentos, nullos, vt laberentur, impulſos</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>) By whoſe hand of prouidence wee know many to be ſupported that they might not fall, none im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peld that they ſhould. And in his anſwer to that 14. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle falſly ſuppoſed to be his, <hi>Fieri non poteſt, vt per quem à peccatis ſurgitur, per eum ad peccata decidatur:</hi> for one and the ſelfe-ſame goodneſſe, to be the life and death of the ſelfe-ſame ſinne, is ſo much beyond improbability, that it is impoſſible. If any then goe onward in the true rode of diuine graces, no doubt but the finger of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty points out his way to happineſſe; but if he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the by pathes of a vicious and depraued diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, his owne corrupt affections beckens him to ruine. To loue then his children, and neglect his enemies, doth neither impaire Gods mercy, nor impeach his iuſtice. But why God ſhould loue this as his childe, neglect that as his enemy, <hi>Nec poſſible eſt comprehendere, nec licitum inueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gara</hi>—, is beyond all lawfulneſſe of enquirie, all ken of apprehenſion. Let this then ſatisfie our deſire of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Et ab illo eſſe, quod ſtatur, &amp; non eſſe ab illo, quod ruitur:</hi> That his prouidence is the ſtaffe and crutch on which we ſo leane that we yet ſtand; our corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the bruzed and broken reed on which, if wee doe leane, we fall. If any flagger at thoſe vnfathomed my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and his reaſon and apprehenſion be ſtrooke dead at the contemplation of Gods eternall, but hidden pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, let him ſeaſon a little his amazement with adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and at laſt ſolace his diſtempered thoughts with that of <hi>Gregory, Qui infactis Dei, &amp;c.</hi> In the abſtruſe and darker myſteries of God, he that ſees not a reaſon, if he ſees his own infirmity, he ſees a ſufficient reaſon why he ſhould not ſee. Me thinkes this ſhould cloy the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite of a greedy inquiſition, and ſatisfie the diſtruſt of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but of too querulous a diſpoſition, which, with the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1982:17"/>eye of curioſitie prying too nicely into the cloſet of Gods ſecrets, are no leſſe dazeled than blinded; if not with profanation, hereſie. Diuine ſecrets ſhould rather tranſport vs with wonder, than prompt vs to enquiry, and bring vs on our knees to acknowledge the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both of Gods power and will, than ranſacke the boſome of the Almighty, for the reuealing of his intents. Is it not bleſſedneſſe enough that God hath made thee his Steward, though not his Secretarie? Will no Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in heauen content thee, but that which is the throne and chaire for omnipotency to ſit on? No treaſury, but that which is the Cabinet and ſtore-houſe of his own ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets? Worme, and no man, take heed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow thou ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt with thy Maker; expoſtulation with God imports no leſſe peremptorineſſe, than danger; and if Angels fell for pride of emulation, where wilt thou tumble for this pride of inquiry? As in matters therefore of vnuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all doubt, where truth hath no verdict, probability finds audience, So in thoſe obſtruct and narrow paſſages of his will, where reaſon cannot informe thee, beleefe is thy beſt intelligencer, and if that want a tongue, make this thy interpreter; ſo thou maiſt euade with leſſe diſtruſt, I am ſure, with more ſafe.</p>
               <p>And at laſt when thou haſt ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>'d all, what either ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or inquiſition can prompe thee to, in a dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, thou muſt cry out with that Iewiſh penitent; <hi>Lord I beleeue, helpe thou my vnbeleefe.</hi> Yea, but how ſhall we here cleare God from this aſperſion, when the Apoſtle is the Herauld to his guilt? <hi>whom he will he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: Induras</hi> is an actiue, and doth alwayes preſuppoſe a paſſiue; And if there be a ſubiect that muſt ſuffer, there muſt be a hand too that muſt inflict. How then can we quit the Almighty of the ſupicion either of tyranny or iniuſtice, ſince he is ſaid to ſend on ſome <hi>the ſpirit of errour,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. and that great Trumpet of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, <hi>Eſay</hi> in his 63. brings in the Iewes, no leſſe mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1982:17"/>than expoſtulating with God, <hi>Quare errar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nos fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Domine? Lord why heſt thou made vs to erre from thy wayes, and hardened our hearts from thy feare?</hi> Theſe inſtances (at the firſt furu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,) beare terrour in their looks, and like ſophiſticated lights in a darke roome, make things ſeeme more vgly than they are; and are but falſe bils, preferred againſt a ſpotleſſe innocent, which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſearch, may conuince of publique erime, but narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcan'd, abſolue him, no leſſe from the act, than the thought of guilt. How God therefore in this is liable to cenſure and miſpriſion, and how both a beholder, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedier of depraued actions; vouchſafe me a little your attentiue parience; and I doubt not, but I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the vnderſtanding of the ſhallow, and to the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my weake Talent, will ſtriue to ſatisfie the waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly iudicious. <hi>Whom he will he hardens.</hi> Some (too nicely tender of the honour of their maker) haue giuen way to an interpretation more modeſt, than authenticke, and interpret, —<hi>indur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>— for <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uritia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> manifeſtare,</hi> ſo that God is not properly ſaid to harden the heart, but rather to manifeſt how hard it is, And to this opinion Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e adherent in his 18 Queſtion vpon <hi>Exodus.</hi> But this holds not with the purpoſe of God, nor with the ſcope and meaning of the Text, which if we compare with others of that nature, wee ſhall finde that Gods <hi>will</hi> hath rather a ſinger in this, than his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation: for ſo in the 10 of <hi>Ioſua</hi> we reade, that'twas the <hi>will</hi> and the ſentence of the Almighty, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites ſhould be hardened; that they might deſerue no mercie, but periſh. Others there are (whoſe opinions bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der neerer vpon truth) which would haue God to be ſaid to harden —<hi>non effectiue, ſed permiſſiuè;</hi> Not by way of Action, but permiſſion, and ſo <hi>Damaſcen</hi> in his third booke <hi>de fide Orthodoxa, cap.</hi> 20. Where his words run thus. <hi>Operaepretium eſt agnoſcere</hi>—. 'Tis a matter no leſſe worthy of knowledge, than obſeruance, that 'tis the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1982:18"/>cuſtome of the Scripture to call Gods permiſſion, his action. So we reade that God ſent his enemies the Ipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſlumber, which is not to be aſcribed to God as an agent, but as a permitter. This gloſſe ſutes well with the approbation of Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> who ſpeaking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally of that of the firſt of the <hi>Romanes, Deus tradidit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llos</hi>— God gaue them vp vnto vile affections, hee there expounds —<hi>tradidit,</hi> by <hi>permiſit,</hi> which he thus illuſtraces by a ſimilitude— As the Generall of an Armie, in the ſweat and brunt of a bloudy day, if he withdraw his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall directions from his ſouldiers, what doth he but expoſe them to the mercie of their enemies? not that he led them into the iawes of danger, but becauſe they were not back't by his encouragement: So God in this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conflict, he deliuers vs not into the hands of our arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enemie he leaues vs to our owne ſtrength, and our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affections drag vs thither with a witneſſe. And hence that dicotomy of <hi>Caietan</hi> claimes his prerogatiue, that God doth harden <hi>Negatiuely,</hi> but not <hi>Poſitiuely,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> diſtinction though it be ſound &amp; Orthodox, yet it doth not exempt vs from ſcruple, for God hath more in the ſtiffeneckt and peruerſe, than a maked and bare permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, otherwiſe we ſhould too weakly diſtance obduration from a leſſer ſinne, for euery ſinne God permits and as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his <hi>Enchir.</hi> 96. <hi>cap. Nihil ſit niſi om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotens fieri velit, vel finend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vt fiat, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l ipſe fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> There's nothing done without the conſent and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Almightie, and that either by his perſon or ſubſtitute. If God therfore be only ſaid to harden man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he permits him to be hardened, why ſhould he not be likewiſe ſaid to ſteale, becauſe he permits man to ſteale? No doubt therefore but God hath a greater ore in this ſinne of hardneing, than in offences of a leſſer bulke. And therefore Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 3. <hi>lib. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iulianum,</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> with many a ſinewed allegation proues; that God doth concurre to the excaeca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion and hardening both of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1982:18"/>the minde and heart,—<hi>Non ſolum, ſecundum paetientiam, &amp; permiſſionem, ſed potentiam, &amp; actionem.</hi> Not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his patience and permiſſion onely, but his power and action: Which poſition hee thus (after) qualifies with a diſtinction. <hi>Obduration</hi> is not onely a <hi>ſinne,</hi> but a <hi>puniſhment</hi> of a ſinne. Now, that which is in obduration meerely of ſinne hath it's pedegree and originall from man onely; but that which is of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that ſinne, from God. And therefore I cannot but approue of that of <hi>Iſiodore, Qui iuſti ſunt, à Deo non impelluntur, vt malifiant; ſed dùm mali iam ſunt, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur, vt deteriores exiſtant,</hi>— According to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they might beleeue a lie, that all might be damned that beleeue not the truth, but haue pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe. I haue as yet but toucht the barke and skinne of the controuerſie, the pith and the kernell is yet vnchewed, and that is,—<hi>Whether God here (as hee is ſaid to harden) be the cauſe of our tranſgreſſions.</hi> Which <hi>quaere</hi> admits a three-fore diſtraction, and difference of opinion. Two of them are extremes, and by hot oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition each of other, they haue both loſt the truth, the third runnes in a midway, and euer directs to ſafety. <hi>Florinus</hi> (whoſe opinion poſterity records as the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a ſeduced errour) with no leſſe peremptorineſſe than blaſpemy hath arraigned the Almighry, and made him not onely the permitter, but the Author of our ſins. The <hi>Seleuciani,</hi> after him, were poiſoned with that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, &amp; the <hi>Libertines</hi> laboured in the defence therof. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and his diſciples, dreampt of a <hi>ſummum malum,</hi> and vpon that phantaſie grounded their aſſertion, that God the <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> is to be ſeene onely in our good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but euery depraued Act had its deriuation from their <hi>ſummum malum.</hi> But thoſe of a more ſolid and well tempered iudgement, whom the influence of the Spirit had taught a moderation, or the danger of Inquiſition
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1982:19"/>forbad curioſity, dare not with <hi>Florinus</hi> impute (here) ſinne vnto God, yet maintaine againſt the <hi>Manichees,</hi> that God is not a bare and idle ſpectator, but powerfull ouer, although no actor in the ſinne, Not in the ſinne, as it is meerely a ſinne, but in the ſinne as 'tis a puniſhment of ſinne. And therefore in euery tranſgreſſion of ours, there are foure thing, remarkeable, 1 <hi>Subiectum, ſeu materiale,</hi> he ſubiect in which ſinne ſubſiſts, and that is two-fold. 1 <hi>Subſtantia,</hi> the ſubſtance, or rather the faculties of the reaſonable ſoule, in which originall ſinne is ſo riueted, that the naturall man can by no meanes purge himſelfe of that hereditary contagion; or <hi>Actio bona,</hi> on, which all our actuall ſinnes are grounded. 2 <hi>Formale,</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie, or obliquity of the action. For euery ſinne is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the tranſgreſſion of the Law, and in the ſinner there's nothing ſinne but this. 3 <hi>Reatus,</hi> The guilt of this enormitie, which makes. vs liable to eternall death. 4 <hi>Poena,</hi> the puniſhment inflicted vpon the guilty, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temporall, or eternall, or both. Now wee may not charge God with the obliquitie of the action, for that proceedes from a peruerſe, and a ſeduced will, but the ſubſtance of the action (as the Schoolemen ſpeake) that hath its originall from God. And therefore we conſider ſinne, either <hi>vt malum culpae.</hi> as 'tis a violation of Gods law, or <hi>vt malum poenae.</hi> as a puniſhment laid vpon vs for the violation of that Law: So <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.25. <hi>The Gentiles tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the truth of God into a lye,</hi> There's <hi>malum culpae.</hi> And it followes immediatly at the 26 <hi>verſe.</hi> For this cauſe God gaue them vp into vile affections, There's <hi>malum poenae.</hi> Now God is author of the ſecond, not the firſt. If miſts ſtill hang on the eyes of clouded errour, I thus diſpell them with that of <hi>Hugo de Sancto Victore— Deus malis poteſtatem ſolam tribuit, non voluntatem, quià licet ex ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us permiſſione ſit, quod malum poſſunt, ex inſpiratione tamen non eſt quod malum volunt.</hi> God onely giues power to the wicked, not will, that although it be by his permiſſion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1982:19"/>that we can doe euill, yet it is not by his inſpiration that we will doe euill. And therefore as the Schooles doe commonly diſtinguiſh of the decree of God, ſo muſt wee of the execution of that decree, which is either <hi>per effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eutiam,</hi> when the diuine power doth worke any thing with, or without the creature, or <hi>ſecundum permiſſionem,</hi> when the creature hath leaue to worke without the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of that power. Neither will it ſauour of imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, if we inſert here that diſtinction of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in <hi>efficientem &amp; deſerentem:</hi> Into a <hi>releeuing and forſaking prouidence,</hi> for whenſoeuer God withdrawes his eſpeciall aid and aſſiſtance from vs, man is hurried where his owne corrupter appetite, not Gods grace car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth him. <hi>Adam</hi> fell as ſoone as the influence of Gods grace ceaſed, and without the ſupportance of the ſame grace we all fall, with no leſſe certainty of perill, than danger of reſtitution. When the Sunne ſets, we ſee dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe followes immediatly vpon the face of the earth, and yet the Sunne is not the efficient cauſe of darkneſſe, but the deficient; ſo when the Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhall forſake vs, the darkneſſe of errour, muſt needs poſſeſſe the vnderſtanding, and the will muſt miſtake in her choice and execution. She muſt <hi>neceſſitate conſequentiae, non conſequentis.</hi> The neceſſitie is grounded on a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in Logicke, not any influence in Nature. And here we may borrow a true gloſſe for that in the 2 <hi>Acts,</hi> where it is ſaid that Chriſt was deliuered into the hands of the wicked, by the determinate counſell &amp; fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. We muſt not thinken hat God was the ſetter in this villany, that he conſpired with <hi>Iudas</hi> in his treaſon, or with <hi>Pilate</hi> in his bloudy ſentence: But that he only gaue way to their attempts, and ſuffered them to crucifie the Lord of glory. Yea, but why did not God curbe them in their cruell proceedings? Why ſhould his conniuence betray the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of Innovence? Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſhall anſwer for me. <hi>Quia melius iudicauit de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> malis
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1982:20"/>bene-facere, quàm mala nullae eſſe permittere.</hi> To extract good out of euill was peculiar onely to omnipotency and goodneſſe; and therefore no leſſe ſolid than charitable is that caucat of <hi>Du-Pleſſes—Malè quaeritur, vnde malum eſſiciatur.</hi> It is an ill curioſity to ſeeke an efficient cauſe of ill. Let this then ſatisfie modeſten quiry that it is with the ſinner as with an vntuned Inſtrument, and the Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, the ſound is from the finger of him that toucheth it, but the iarring from the Inſtrument.</p>
               <p>That our diſcourſe then with the time may draw to wards a Period, we inuolue and wrap vp in this one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction the very iuice and ſubſtance of the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Sinne is conſiderable two waies, <hi>ante commiſſionem,</hi> before the Commiſſion, <hi>Sic ſe Deus habet negatiuè, tum reſpectu voluntatis, tum productionis.</hi> God doth neither worke with vs, nor countenance vs in the act of ſinning. <hi>Poſt commiſſionem,</hi> after the Commiſſion, <hi>ſic Deus deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat, &amp; ordinat peccatum.</hi> God ſets bounds to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of wicked men, and ſo mannages the diſorder in ſin, that contrary to the nature of ſinne, and the intent of the ſinner, it ſhall redound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his glory.</p>
               <p>We inculcate then, that God is not the <hi>author,</hi> but the <hi>orderer</hi> of ſinne. Hee cauſeth the <hi>worke,</hi> not the <hi>fault;</hi> the <hi>effect,</hi> not the <hi>delinquencie,</hi> working <hi>by,</hi> not <hi>in</hi> miſchiefe. Wherein, according to the rules of Logicke, <hi>the finall and impulſiue cauſes euer ſo diſtinguiſh the actions, that two doing the ſame thing to a diuers intent, are notwithſtanding ſaid not to doe the ſame.</hi> So God gaue his Sonne, and Chriſt himſelfe, and <hi>Iudas</hi> Chriſt, (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) why is God here holy, and man guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? <hi>Niſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in re vnâ quam fecerunt, non eſt cauſa vna ob quam fecerunt.</hi> I ſhut vp all with that ſtate of <hi>Fulgentius</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>ad M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cinum cap.</hi> 13. Where hauing long houered ouer this queſtion, <hi>An peccata ſiant ex prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatione?</hi> He at laſt thus reſolues it. <hi>Potuit Deus, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut voluit, praedeſtiuare quoſdam ad gloriam, quoſdam ad
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1982:20"/>poenam, ſed quos praedeſtinauit ad gloriam, praedeſtinauit ad iuſtitiam, quos autem praedeſtinauit ad poenam, non praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinauit ad culpam.</hi> God when hee ſaues any man doth predeſtinate him as well to the meanes, as to the end. But in the reprobation of a ſinner, God deſtines the ſinner onely to the puniſhment; foreſeeing, but not determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe ſinnes which ſhall in time draw Gods puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments downe vpon him.</p>
               <p>Doe our corruptions harden then, and God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth? Take heed you <hi>Pharaohs</hi> of the world, you which perſecute the poore Iſraelite in his way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſpurre not the goodneſſe of the Almighty to reuenge, or iuſtice. <hi>Laeſa patientia fit ſuror</hi>—, trample too much on the necke of patience, you will turne it to fury. It is true, God hath feet of Lead (clemency intermixt with ſlowneſſe of reuenge) but he hath hands of iron, they will grinde and bruiſe into powder, when they are dared to combat.</p>
               <q>Sera venit, ſed certa venit vindicta Deorum.</q>
               <p>Procraſtination of diuine iuſtice is euer waited on no leſſe with a certainty of puniſhment than ruine. What ſhall wee doe then (wretched, miſerable that we are) or to whom ſhall we flie for ſuccour? The good S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> tells vs, —<hi>à Deo irato, ad Deum placatum</hi>—, from the tribunall of his iuſtice, to his throne of mercy, and compaſſion. That of <hi>Anſelmus</hi> was moſt admirable —<hi>Et ſi Domine ego commiſi vnde me damnare potes, tu ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men non amiſiſti, vnde me ſaluare potes</hi>—. O bleſſed Ieſus, though I haue committed thoſe tranſgreſſions for which thou maiſt condemne mee, yet thou haſt not loſt thoſe compaſſions by which thou maiſt ſaue me. If our ſoules were in ſuch a ſtraight, that wee ſaw hell opening her mouth vpon vs, like the red ſea before the Iſraelites; the damned and vgly fiends, purſuing vs behinde, like the Egyptians, on the right hand, an on the left; death and ſea ready to ingulſe vs, yet vpon a broken heart, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſguiſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1982:21"/>ſorrow, would I ſpeake to you in the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>Moſes,—Stand ſtill, ſtand ſtill, behold the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord.</hi> Thou then which art oppreſt with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and clamour of thy ſinnes, and wanteſtan aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate either to intercede, or pitty, heare the voice of the <hi>Lambe, —Cry vnto me, I will heare thee out of my holy hill.</hi> Is any heauily loaden with the weight of his offences, or groanes vnder the yoke and tyrannie of manifold temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? —<hi>Come vnto me, I will refreſh thee</hi>—. Doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hunger after righteouſneſſe? behold, <hi>I am the bread of life, take, eat, here is my body.</hi> Doth any thirſt after the waies of grace? loe, <hi>I am a liuing ſpring, come, drinke, here is my bloud:</hi> my bloud that was ſhed for <hi>many</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes; for <hi>many,</hi> not for all. Hath ſinne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer thee? or doth it reigne in thy mortall heart? are the wounds of thy tranſgreſſions ſo deepe that they cannot be ſearched? or ſo old, that they corrupt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie? where is the Samaritan that will either binde them vp, or powre in oyle? But art thou not yet dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes? are not thy vlcers paſt cure? are there any ſeeds of true life remaining? is there any motion of repentance in thy ſoule? will thy pulſe of remorſe beate a little? haſte thou but a touch of ſorrow? a ſparke of contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? a graine of ſaith? know there is <hi>oyle of comfort for him which mournes in Sion.</hi> Not a teare drops from thee with ſincerity which is either vnpittied, or vnpreſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,—<hi>God puts it into his bottle.</hi> On the other ſide, is there a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in thee? an heart vnmollified? a ſtone that will not be bruized? a flint vnmalleable? I both mourne for it, and leaue it: But is this <hi>heart of ſtone</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and is there giuen thee a <hi>heart of fleſh?</hi> is it ſoft and tender with remorſe? truly ſacrificed to ſorrow? know there is <hi>balme of Gilead for the broken heart,</hi> balme that will both refreſh and cure it. Thou then which groaneſt in the ſpirit, and art drawne out (as it were) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contrition for thy ſinnes; thou which haſt <hi>waſht thy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1982:21"/>hands in innocence,</hi> goe cheerefully <hi>to the altar of thy God,</hi> vnbinde thy ſacrifice, lay it on. But haſt thou done it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely? from thy heart? lurkes there no falſhood there? is all <hi>ſwept cleane and garniſhed?</hi> doth the countenance of that ſmile as cheerefully, as the other ſeemes to doe of the outward man? if ſo. thy fire is well kindled, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar burnes clearly, the <hi>ſauour of thy incenſe ſhall pierce the clowds.</hi> But is this repentance diſguized? hath it a touch of diſſimulation in it? is not thy olde rankor cleane diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorged, but muſt thou againe to thy former vomit? hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, thy Altar is without fire, thy incenſe without ſmoke, it ſhall neuer touch the noſtrils of the Almighty, thy prayers in his eares ſound like braſſe, and tinkle like an ill-tuned Cimball; all this formality of zeale is but a diſeaſe of the lip: <hi>giue me thy heart my ſonne,</hi> I will haue that, or none, and that cleane too, waſht both from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and guilt. That ſubtill fallacy of the eye pointing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen, that baſe hypocriſie of the knee kiſſing the earth, that ſeeming auſterity of the hand martyring thy breaſt, gaines from me neither applauſe, nor bleſſing; the example of a Phariſee could haue chid thee to ſuch an outſide of deuotion,—<hi>Qui pectus ſuum tundit, &amp; ſe non corrigit, aggrauat peccata, non tollit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> where there is an outward percuſſion of the breaſt, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of the inward man, there is rather an aggrauation of ſinne, than a releaſe; theſe blanchings, and guildings, and varniſhings of externall zeale, are as odious in the eie of God, as thoſe of body in a true Chriſtian; this gloſſe, this paint of demureneſſe ſpeakes but our whoredomes in religion, &amp; the integrity of that man is open both to cenſure and ſuſpition, that is expoſed either to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of it, or the approbation. A villaine is a villaine howſoever his garbe or habite ſpeake him otherwiſe, and an hypocrite is no leſſe, though ſleeked ouer with an externall ſanctity, &amp; dreſt in the affectations of a preciſer cut. Let vs be <hi>truely that</hi> what we <hi>ſeeme to be,</hi> and not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1982:22"/>
                  <hi>ſeeme</hi> what we are not; let there be dores &amp; caſements in our breaſts that men may ſee the loyaley twixt our heart and tongue, and how our thoughts whiſper to our tongue, and how our tongue ſpeakes them to the world. A way with thoſe Meteors and falſe-fires of Religion, which not onely by-path vs in a blinded zeale, but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leade others in our ſteps of errour. Let vs put off the old man in our pride, vaine-glorie, hypocriſie, enuy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, malice, and (that foule diſeaſe of the times, and vs) <hi>vncharitableneſſe;</hi> and let vs put on the new man in ſinceritie, faith, repentance, ſobrietie, brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, loue, and (what without it diſparages the tongue both, of men, and Angels) <hi>charitie;</hi> then at length all teares ſhall be wiped away from our eyes, and we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that euerlaſting benediction. —<hi>Come yee children, inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world.</hi>— To which, the Lord bring vs for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to whom be praiſe and power aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed now, and for euermore. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1982:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
